<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A booke of secrets shewing diuers waies to make and prepare all sorts of inke, and colours: as blacke, white, blew, greene, red, yellow, and other colours. Also to write with gold and siluer, or any kind of mettall out of the pen: with many other profitable secrets, as to colour quils and parchment of any colour: and to graue with strong water in steele and iron. ... Translated out of Dutch into English, by W.P. Hereunto is annexed a little treatise, intituled, instructions for ordering of wines: shewing how to make wine, that it may continue good and faint not ... Written first in Italian, and now newly translated into English, by W.P.</title>
            <title>Ettliche Künste, auff mancherley Weisz Dinten und allerhand Farben zu bereyten. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3355</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103623</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839372</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839372</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3783</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16436)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3783)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 282:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A booke of secrets shewing diuers waies to make and prepare all sorts of inke, and colours: as blacke, white, blew, greene, red, yellow, and other colours. Also to write with gold and siluer, or any kind of mettall out of the pen: with many other profitable secrets, as to colour quils and parchment of any colour: and to graue with strong water in steele and iron. ... Translated out of Dutch into English, by W.P. Hereunto is annexed a little treatise, intituled, instructions for ordering of wines: shewing how to make wine, that it may continue good and faint not ... Written first in Italian, and now newly translated into English, by W.P.</title>
                  <title>Ettliche Künste, auff mancherley Weisz Dinten und allerhand Farben zu bereyten. English.</title>
                  <author>Phillip, William, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>W. P., fl. 1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Adam Islip for Edward White, and are to be sold at his shop at the little north dore of Pouls, at the signe of the Gun,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1596.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.P. = William Phillip.</note>
                  <note>Part 1 is a translation of: Ettliche Küntse, auff mancherley Weisz Dinten und allerhand Farben zu bereyten.</note>
                  <note>Italian original of part 2 not traced.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf has an arabesque pattern on the recto, but no text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Colors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Engraving --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wine and wine making --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3783:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3783:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3783:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3783:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BOOKE OF SECRETS: Shewing diuers waies to make and prepare all <hi rend="blackletterType">ſorts of Inke, and Colours: as Blacke, White, Blew, Gréene, Red, Yellow, and other Colours. Alſo to write with Gold and Siluer, or any kind of Mettall out of the Pen: with many other profitable ſecrets, as to colour Quils and Parchment of any colour: and to graue with ſtrong Water in Steele and Iron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neceſſarie to be knowne of all Scriueners, Painters, and others that delight in ſuch Arts. Tranſlated out of Dutch into Engliſh, by <hi>W. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereunto is annexed a little Treatiſe, intituled, <hi>Jnstructions for ordering of Wines:</hi> Shewing how to make Wine, That it may continue good and faint not, Neither become ſower, nor looſe colour. And how you may remedie faint Wine, take away the hoari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, with other inſtructions for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written first in Italian, and now newly tranſlated into Engliſh, by</hi> W. P.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by Adam Iſlip for Edward White, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the little North dore of Pouls, at the ſigne of the Gun. 1596.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3783:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3783:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ A Booke of Secrets, ſhewing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers waies to make and prepare all ſorts of Inke and colours.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>And first to make Inke in diuers maners.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is firſt to bee vnderſtood that if you wil make a great quantitie of Inke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you muſt encreaſe the waight, and meaſure, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the proportion you meane to make, as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, if you will make ten quarts of Inke, then take foure quarts of water, and ſixe quarts of vineger and wine, that is, three of each ſort, which together with the water make ten quarts, and ſo muſt you doe with other quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, either more or leſſe. The like muſt you doe in the waight of your other ſtuffe that belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth therevnto, as for a pint of water, ſixe oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of gaule, foure ounces of victriall, and foure ounces of gum, and if you take foure quarts of water (which is eight pints) if you giue to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pint his proportion, then multiplying eight by ſixe they make fortie eight, ſo many ounces of gaule muſt you put to ten quarts, mixed as afore ſaid with wine, vineger, &amp; water, and of victrial and gum, of each xxxii ounces, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the firſt proportion, and ſo muſt you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue your quantities, of waight and meaſure in each proportion, as you are minded to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
<pb facs="tcp:3783:4"/>the ſame, as in this treatiſe you ſhal read.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make Inke to write vpon paper.</head>
               <p>Take halfe a pint of water, a pint wanting a quarter of wine, and as much vineger, which being mixed together make a quart &amp; a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a pint more, then take ſix ounces of gauls beaten into ſmall pouder, and ſifted through a ſiue, put this pouder into a pot by it ſelfe, and poure halfe the water, wine, and vineger into it, take likewiſe foure ounces of victriall, and beat it into pouder, and put it alſo in a pot by it ſelfe, whereinto put a quarter of the wine, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; vineger that remaineth, and to the other quarter, put foure ounces of gum Arabike bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to pouder, that done, couer the three pots cloſe, and let them ſtand three or foure daies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſtirring them euery day three or foure times, on the firſt day ſet the pot with gaules on the fire, and when it begins to ſeeth, ſtir it about till it be throughly warme, then ſtraine it through a cloath into another pot, and mixe it with the other two pots, ſtirring them well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and being couered, then let it ſtand three daies, till thou meaneſt to vſe it, on the fourth day, when it is ſetled, poure it out, and it wil be good inke. If there remaine any dregs behind, poure ſome raine water (that hath ſtand long in a tubor veſſell into it, for the older the water is, the better it is, and keepe that vntill you make more inke, ſo it is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clean water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:3783:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>To make Inke for parchment.</head>
               <p>Make it in all points like to the inke afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, only take a pint of water, &amp; of vineger and wine a pint more, that is, of each halfe a pint.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another ſort of Inke.</head>
               <p>Take a quart of cleare water, and put it in a glaſſe, put into it thirteene ounces beaten vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triall, let it ſtand three daies, and ſtir it three or foure times euery day, then take thirteene oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of beaten gaules, and put them into a new earthen pot, that is wel leaded, poure into them a quart of cleane water, that done, ſet it on the fire, and let it ſeeth till it conſumeth about a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger deepe, but ſuffer it not to ſeeth ſo faſt that it ſeeth ouer the pots brim, then ſtrain it through a wolle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cloath, into another pot, that is leaded, poure into the cloath a cup full of good vineger, and ſtrain it though likewiſe, that done, if there remaineth any thing in the cloath, caſt it away, then put into the matter, foure or fiue ounces of beaten gum and ſtir them well together, then againe ſtraine them through a cleane wollen cloath, and poure into it a cup full of good vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ſtraine it through the cloath, and let it ſtand till it be coole, then put it into a ſtraight-necked glaſſe, ſtop both the glaſſes well, till you haue occaſion to vſe them, then take of each wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a little quantitie, and mix them together, ſo haue you good inke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another of the ſame ſort, but eaſie to make.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:3783:5"/>
               <p>Take the beaten gauls, and put them in the water doe the like with the victriall in a pot by it ſelf let thoſe two waters ſtand, and when you haue cauſe to vſe inke, poure out of each pot a like quantitie, and it will be blacke, then put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it a little beaten gum, &amp; it will bee good inke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>Take a quart of ſtrong wine, put it into a new pot, and ſet it on a ſoft fire till it be hote, but let it not ſeeth, then put into it foure ounces of gauls, two ounces and a halfe of gum Arabike, and two ounces of victriall, al beaten into ſmal pouder, and ſifted through a ſiue, ſtirre it with a wooden ſticke, and it will be good inke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>Take an ounce of beaten gaule, three or four ounces of gum Arabicke, put them together in a pot with raine water, and when the gum is almoſt conſumed, ſtrain it through a cloath, and put into it almoſt halfe a cup of victriall beaten to pouder.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>Take a pint of beere, put into it an ounce of gaules beaten to pouder, let it ſeeth till it ſeeme ſomewhat red, then put to it three quarters of an ounce of greene victriall, in ſmall pouder, and let it ſeeth againe, when you take it off the fire,
<pb facs="tcp:3783:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>caſt into it three quarters of an ounce of gum, and a ſmall peece of alum, both in pouder, and ſtir them all together till it be cold.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>Take two handfull of gauls, cut each gaule either into three or four peeces, poure into them a pint of beere or wine, (which you wil) then let it ſtand eight houres, ſtraine it from the gaules, and put victriall therein, and to the victriall a third part of gum, ſet it on the fire to warm, but let it not ſeeth, and it will bee good inke: and of thoſe gaules you may make inke foure or fiue times more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make inke vpon a ſuddaine, to ſerue in an extremitie.</head>
               <p>Take a wax candle, and light it, hold it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a cleane baſon or a candelſticke, till the ſmoke of the candle hangeth theron, then put a little warme gum water into it, which tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together will be good inke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To keepe Inke that it ſinketh not into the paper neither that it come not off, and that moths nor miſe hurt not the paper.</head>
               <p>Take the ſhels of hazell nuts, and put them into the inke, and it will not ſinke through the paper.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3783:6"/>
               <p>And that it may not come off, put a little ſalt into it.</p>
               <p>To keepe that neither Miſe nor eat or fret the paper, put a little wormewood water into the inke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To write without inke, that it may not be ſeen, vnleſſe the paper be wet with water.</head>
               <p>Take pouder of victriall, and put it into a cleane inkehorne, put a little cleane water to it, when the victriall is diſſolued, write with it either vpon paper or parchment, and let it drie, and it cannot bee read: when you will read it, take halfe a pint of water, and put thereto an ounce of pouder of gaules, mix them well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then ſtraine them through a linnen cloath into a cleane pot, then draw the paper through the water, and the writing will be clacke, as if it had ben written with inke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To take Inke out of paper or parchment.</head>
               <p>Take <hi>Colofoniam,</hi> which is called <hi>pix grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> beat it ſmall, and caſt it on the paper that is written, then wet a cloath, and lay it on the <hi>Colofoniam,</hi> vpon the cloath lay ſome freſh horſe dung, &amp; vpon that ſet a ſmooth tile ſtone, then if it be in winter let it ſtand a whole night, but if it bee ſummer, let it ſtand but from mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning till nine of the clocke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Otherwiſe.</head>
               <p>Take <hi>Salarmoniacke,</hi> and alum, ſtill it in a
<pb facs="tcp:3783:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>limbeck, and with this water wet the writing and it will goe out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of red colour, and firſt of Braſill.</head>
               <p>You muſt take care when you ſeeth Braſill, that you do it when the element is clear, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out clouds raine, or wind, otherwiſe it will not be good you muſt make it thus:</p>
               <p>Take quicklime poure raine water vpon it, let it ſtand all night, in the morning poure the water ſoftly from the lime, or ſtraine it through a cloath, &amp; for a quart of water, take an ounce of Braſill, let it ſeeth till it be halfe conſumed, then put into it one ounce of beaten alum, one ounce of gum Arabike, two ounces of gum of a Cheritree, or elſe two ounces of cleane glue, ſtraine it from the wood: you may likewiſe put into it ſome chalke beaten to pouder.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To ſeeth Braſill another way.</head>
               <p>To an ounce of Braſill, take the third part of a quart of beere, wine, or vineger, put it in a new pot<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let it ſtand a night, in the morning ſet it on the fire, and let it ſeeth till it be halfe conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, then for euery ounce of Braſill, take two penny worth of alum, beaten to pouder, and as much beaten gum Arabike, ſtir them wel toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and let them ſeeth againe, but if you deſire to haue it ſomewhat darke, then ſcrape a little chalke into it: when it ſeetheth, let it not ſeeth ouer the pot, and being cold, ſtrain it through a cloath, and put it into a glaſſe well ſtopped.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:3783:7"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another red colour.</head>
               <p>Mingle ſalt and honny together in a baſon, let it ſtand eight daies, then ſeeth it, and it will be a red colour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Purple colour.</head>
               <p>Take two pound of blew Heidleber, two ounces of alum, one ounce of aſhes of copper, which you may haue at the braſiars, a pint of water, put them into a ketle, let it ſeeth till it conſume two fingers deepe, when it is cold, ſtraine it through a clout, in a cleane glaſſe or pot, let it ſtand a while, then ſtraine it into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pot, and let it ſtand till it be thicke enough.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make Roſin.</head>
               <p>Take ſtrong vineger, or wine, and put pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of alum therin, when the alum is diſſolued, then make a ſtrong and thicke lee with quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime, and take foure times as much Braſill as your alum waieth, put it in a clout, and hang it in the lee, and let it ſtand a day &amp; a night, then ſtraine it, and hang the Braſill again in the lee, and let it ſtand as long as it did the firſt time, which doe in like manner three or foure times, when you haue done ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let it ſtand and drie, and it is perfect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another Roſin.</head>
               <p>Take two parts red lead, one part white
<pb facs="tcp:3783:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>lead, and mingle them together, or take <hi>Auri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pigmentum</hi> and red lead, of each a like quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and mingle them together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Fire colour.</head>
               <p>Take ſout of a chimney, and a little alum, let them boile, then take gineper, granded with water, and temper it together, with alum and gum Arabike.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Tawny colour.</head>
               <p>Take blacking, and mingle it with red lead and gum Arabike.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Yellow colour.</head>
               <p>Take hauthorne berries, gather them eight daies after Saint <hi>Laurence</hi> day, bruſe them and put a little beaten alum vnto them, ſtirre them well together, and let them ſtand one night, and it will be a faire yellow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another good yellow.</head>
               <p>Take the barke of a tree, cut off the outſide, and throw it away, cut the reſt in ſmall peeces, and poure water vnto them, let them ſeeth two or three times, then put pouder of alum into it, ſtirre them well together, and let them ſeeth againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another yellow.</head>
               <p>Mix ſaffron with the yolke of an eg, and it maketh a faire ſhining colour.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:3783:8"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Otherwiſe.</head>
               <p>Put ſaffron and alum inco a clout, and put vineger into it, and ſtrain it out: or take ſaffron, the yolke of an eg, gum Arabike and alum, and mix them together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Auripigmentum.</head>
               <p>Take gaule of Eeles, or of other great fiſhes, or oxe gaule, put ſome vineger to it, and a little chalke, and make a paſte thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Greene colour.</head>
               <p>Take the blacke berries that grow on the hauthorne tree, and gather them eight daies after Michaelmas day, bruſe them, poure wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto them, and put therein a little beaten a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, ſtir them well together, and let them ſtand two daies and a night, &amp; it will be good greene.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A faire greene colour.</head>
               <p>Take honie, put a little quantitie of vineger more then the honie is, into it, mingle it well in a leaded or a copper pot, ſtop it well, and ſet it twelue daies vnder another pot, and put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a little chalke.</p>
               <p>Alſo take copper plates, put them in a cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per pot, and put ſtilled vineger to them, ſet them in a warme place, till the vineger become blew, then put it into another leaded pot, poure vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb facs="tcp:3783:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>into it againe, let it ſtand ſo till it become blew, this doe ſo many times, till you thinke you haue inough, then let it ſtand till it be thick.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To temper or prepare Verdigreece.</head>
               <p>Grind it with wine, and put two or three drops of honny to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make good greene.</head>
               <p>Take copper plates, let them lie ſix months in vmeger in a warme place, then take them out, and drie them in the ſun, and the flower you find vpon the plates, ſcrape it of, for that is the colour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Blew colour.</head>
               <p>Grind chalke with the iuice of the elder ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſtraine it through a clout, put a little alum water vnto it, let it drie, and keep it til you need.</p>
               <p>In the ſame ſort you may make colour of the blew corne flowers.</p>
               <p>Alſo the iuice of the blew corn flowers alone, with alum and gum tempered together, is a good blew.</p>
               <p>Alſo mulberies boiled with alum.</p>
               <p>Alſo take blew corn flowers that are not too much blowne, and gather them in a morning before the ſun riſeth plucke the blew leafe, and let not any of the white come among them, and put them into a copper kettle, and hang it in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:3783:9"/>water, till they be drie, keepe them in a glaſſe well couered. When you wil make colour of them, then take ſome of the blew leaues, and put them into a drinking glaſſe, poure water into them, till it be thicke like dowe, let it ſtand couered twelue houres, then preſſe the liquor through a cloath into another glaſſe, and put a little glue into it, and ſet it in a warme place, or elſe in whote water, vntill it bee drie and thicke to vſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make Azure.</head>
               <p>Take one ounce of white lead, nine ounces of <hi>Indicum,</hi> pour good vineger vnto it, put them in a leaded diſh, let them ſeeth well, and that which ſwimmeth on the top is the colour.</p>
               <p>Or take two parts of chalk made of egſhels, one part of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erdigreece, one part of <hi>Salarmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acke,</hi> mingle them together with ſtrong vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, put them in a new pot, ſtop it well, that no aire iſſue forth, ſet it in a warme place for a month long, and it will be Azure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To temper or prepare Azure.</head>
               <p>Waſh it wel in cleane water, and that ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth on the top, caſt it away, and that which lieth in the bottome, is good, doe ſo three or four times one after another, and let the water bee cleane poured from it, then take white of egs, that are well beaten, put thereto a little beaten gum Arabike, and let it ſtand till the gum is
<pb facs="tcp:3783:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>diſſolued, then put the Azure into it, and mingle them well together, ſtraine it through a linnen cloath into an inkehorne, and vſe it when you will.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A faire blew.</head>
               <p>Grind the Azure with faire water very well vpon a ſtone, then put it in a horne or ſhell, and pour water theron, ſtir them wel together, then let them ſtand half a day, then pour out the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and take the gaule of a great fiſh, and grind it with gum and the white of egs, and vſe it when you thinke good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>White colour. To write with chalke out of a pen vpon blacke ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles or paper.</head>
               <p>Grind quicklime, egſhels, and chalke, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the milke of a goat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make chalke of egſhels.</head>
               <p>Take egſhels, and let them lie three daies in vineger, then waſh them well in faire water, drie them in the ſun, and beat them to pouder, then grind them vpon a ſtone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A good white colour.</head>
               <p>Take white glaſſe wel beaten to pouder, put thereto ſome brimſtone in pouder, and keepe it
<pb facs="tcp:3783:10"/>in a pot wel couered, ſet it vpon a ſoft fire, til it be red hote, then let it coole, and grind it on a ſtone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Gold colours.</head>
               <head>To make Aurum Muſicum.</head>
               <p>Take one ounce of <hi>Salarmoniack,</hi> one ounce of quick ſiluer, one ounce of <hi>Conterfein,</hi> halfe an ounce of brimſtone, bruſe the brimſtone, ſet it on the fire, but let it not be ouer hote leaſt it bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, or become black, then take the <hi>Salarmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack,</hi> &amp; the quick ſiluer, being in pouder, mix them wel together, then mingle them with the brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, ſtir them well &amp; quickly with a ſticke, till the brimſtone becommeth hard, then let it cool, grind it on a ſtone, and put it in a glaſſe with a long neck wel ſtopped with luttum, and ſet it in a pan with aſhes, make a fire vnder it, and let it ſtand halfe a day; in ſuch maner, not ouer hote, till a yellow ſmoke riſeth vpon it, and when the yellow ſmoke is gone, then it is prepared.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Otherwiſe.</head>
               <p>Take an ounce of Cin, melt it in a pot, put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it half an ounce of Tartarum, &amp; one ounce of quick ſiluer, ſtir them together, till it bee hard, &amp; congealed into a cake, then grind it well vpon a ſtone, put to it one ounce of beaten <hi>Salarmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack,</hi> mix them wel together, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> melt one ounce of brimſtone, but make it not too hote, poure the ground pouder into it, ſtirre it well vntill it bee hard, let it coole, and doe as before is ſaid.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>You muſt temper it thus.</head>
                  <p>Grind it well, waſh it wel in clean water out
<pb facs="tcp:3783:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>of one muſſell ſhell into another, till it bee very cleane, then put it into a pewter pot, put ſome gum water therein, ſtir it about, and write ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with, let it drie, and poliſh it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Argentum Muſicum.</head>
               <p>Melt an ounce of Tin, &amp; put thereto an ounce of Tartarum, an ounce of quick ſiluer, ſtirre it well tu it be cold, beat it in a morter, then grind it on a ſtone, temper it with gum water, &amp; write 0 therewith, then poliſh it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To write a gold colour.</head>
               <p>Take a new laid hens eg, make a hole at the one end of it, and let the ſubſtance out, then take the yolk of an eg without the white, and foure times as much in quantity of quick ſiluer, grind them well together, ſlop the hole of the egſhell with chalke &amp; the white of an eg, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lay it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a hen that ſitteth with ſix egs more, let hir ſit vpon it three weekes; then breake it vp &amp; write therewith, ſome ſay it muſt bee laid vnder three ſeueral hens, and vnder each hen three weekes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To write with gold out of a penſill.</head>
               <p>Take hony &amp; ſalt a like quantity, grind them wel, put to it a leaf of gold with a little white of an eg, put it into a muſſell ſhel, and let it purifie, temper it with gum water, &amp; write therewith, let it drie, and poliſh it with a tooth.</p>
               <p>Or grind ſaltſtone well with the white of an eg, put into it a leafe or two of gold, and write therewith as before.</p>
               <p>Or grind a leaf of ſiluer or gold very ſmal with gum water, and waſh it in a muſſell ſhell as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:3783:11"/>
               <head>To write all mettals out of the pen.</head>
               <p>Grind criſtall well, temper it with gum wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or the white of an eg, write with it, then let it drie, then take the mettal which you wil, and rub it vpon the letters writen, till the letter bee well coloured with the color of the mettall, then poliſh it with a tooth.</p>
               <p>Or take criſtall and pomeſtone, both ground very ſmall, put thereto a little verdigreece, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten likewiſe to pouder, and put them all into a leaded pipkin, ſet it vpon a ſoft fire, but let it not bee too hote, let it not ſtand ſo long on the fire, that it becommeth as blacke as a coale, then grind it on a ſtone, temper it with gum water, write with it as aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A good gold colour.</head>
               <p>Take linſeed oile, put into it a little <hi>Aloe Epaticum,</hi> and alum, let them ſeeth well in a lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded pot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To lay gold vpon any thing.</head>
               <p>Take red lead, temper it with linſeed oile, write with it, and lay gold vpon it, ſo let it drie, and poliſh it.</p>
               <p>Or lay gum Arabike in vineger, ſo long til it waxeth white, take it out and put it into the white of egs, till it melteth, write with it, when it is almoſt drie, lay the gold vpon it, then let it ſtand one night, and poliſh it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:3783:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>To lay gold vpon glaſſe.</head>
               <p>Grind chalke, and red lead in like qantity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, with linſeed oile, lay it on, when it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt drie, lay your gold vpon it, and being well dried, poliſh it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>End of the colours.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to graue in yron and ſteel, or in other mettals with ſtrong water.</head>
               <p>FOr as much as that euery man in this our age, is giuen to write, learne, and practiſe all manner of arts, I am of opinion it will not be vnprofitable vnto ſuch as are deſirous to learn, it I ſet ſomewhat before them that may teach them to write letters, and graue any other thing in freele, yron, or other mettals, which I willingly preſent vnto them, although it be but a ſmall matter, if it be profitable vnto them, I wiſh them to vſe it.</p>
               <p>Take two parts of verdigreece, one part of common ſalt, beat it in a morter, put thereto ſharpe vineger, and when you will graue, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint your plate firſt with red lead tempered with linſeed oile, let it drie, this ſubſtance lay vpon the plate, and the warmer the place is, when it lieth, the ſooner it wil eat in, and when it is drie, take away the pouder, and make the plate cleane againe.</p>
               <p>Or take two parts victriall, one third part
<pb facs="tcp:3783:12"/>
                  <hi>Salarmoniack,</hi> grind it togither vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſtone with brine, and lay it on as aforeſaid, but lay it cold vpon the place where you graue, and ſet it in a ſeller four or fiue houres.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another way to graue with water.</head>
               <p>Take verdigrecce, Mercurie, ſublimated vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triall, &amp; alum, of the one as much as the other, beat them all to pouder, put them into a glaſſe, let them ſtand ſo half a day, &amp; ſtir it often about, then lay wax mingled with linſeed oile, or red lead with linſeed oile, and write in it that you mean to graue, then put the water vpon it, &amp; let it remaine ſo halfe a day, if you wil haue it very deepe, then let it ſtand longer, if you will graue any other worke as images, &amp;c. Then lay the wax vpon the yron or ſteele very thinly on, and draw what you will therein with your inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that it may touch the mettall, then put water into the ſtrokes, and it wil be grauen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another way, but more piercing.</head>
               <p>Take one ounce of verdigreece, half an ounce of <hi>Alum plumoſum,</hi> halfe an ounce of <hi>Salarmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack,</hi> half an ounce of Tartarum, halfe an ounce of victrial, and half an ounce of common ſalt, all beaten to pouder, mingle them together, &amp; pour ſtrong vineger vnto them, let them ſtand one houre, and when you wil graue, write vpon the yron or ſtecle with linſeed oile and red lead, &amp; let it drie, then heat the water aforeſaid in a leaded pan, &amp; let it ſtand on the fire, &amp; hold the yron or ſteel ouer the pan, poure the hote water vpon it with a ſpoon, and let it run again into the pan,
<pb facs="tcp:3783:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>which doe for the ſpace of a quarter of an houre, then rub it off with aſhes or vnſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eact lime, but be ſure that the places you will eat into be all well couered with red lead.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To colour quils and parchment of diuers colors.</head>
               <p>Take the quils, &amp; cut away the fethers, and rub the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wel with a wollen cloath, that the ſkin go clean off, that the quil may be ſmooth, which muſt alwaies be done before you die the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, cut off a little of the end of the quil that the colour may enter into the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lay them in alum water, for halfe a day take them out &amp; drie them, then die them, when they are died, as I wil teach you, let them be wel dried, and ſtrike them ouer with a cloath betweene two fingers, then ſtick them in a bord that is full of holes, and let euery one hauea ſpace berweene it that they touch not together, and drie them in the aire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To die quils greene.</head>
               <p>Take two parts verdigreece, a third part <hi>Salarmoniacke,</hi> grind them well together, ſteepe them in ſtrong vineger, and put the quils into it, and couer them cloſe, let them lie therein till they be green as you deſire to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: you may die likewiſe bones &amp; wood in the ſame manner, lay the quils, wood, or bones, in a leaded pot, poure vineger vpon them, wherein Greekiſh green is mixed, couer it, and ſet it ſeuen daies or more vnder warme horſe dung. You may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo temper verdigreece with vineger, till it bee ſomewhat drie, put the quils into it, let them lie long therein, then take them out, &amp; put them in
<pb facs="tcp:3783:13"/>warm horſe dung, &amp; let them continue therein eighteene daies together: you may die red quils in that ſort and make them greene, alſo take ſtrong vineger, put it in a copper pot, or kettle, put verdigreece into it, let it ſtand til it be green, put the quils into it, &amp; let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lie til they be green.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Red quils.</head>
               <p>Seeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Braſil, as before you are taught, hauing firſt laid them in alum water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Yellow quils.</head>
               <p>Seeth them in yellow colour, as before you are taught what you ſhall do with the barke of aple trees.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Blacke quils.</head>
               <p>Seeth beaten gaules in ſtrong vineger, lay the quils in it, and let them ſeeth likewiſe, then lay them in the white of egs, and put vnto them the green pils of walnuts, and let them ſeeth all together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To colour parchment and velim of diuers colors.</head>
               <p>Take as much parchment or velim as you will, and faſten it at the corners and ſides with nailes vnto a bord, with the ſmooth ſide out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, annoint it then with what colour you will, be it yellow, blew, red or black, ſuch as you find ſet down in this booke, let it drie well, then ſtroke it ouer, and let it drie in a place, where no duſt is ſtirring.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3783:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>Certaine Instructions for ordering of Wines:</hi> Shewing how to make Wine, that it may continue good and faint not, Neither become ſower, nor looſe colour. And how you may remedie faint Wine, take away the hoari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, with other inſtructions for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the ſame.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the preparation for the Vintage, or gathering in of the grapes, where Wine is made.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the time of the Vintage ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procheth, you muſt prepare and make ready the veſſels in the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where the wines are vſed to be boiled, &amp; the cheſts, baſkets, preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and other inſtruments that are fit for euery kind of worke belonging therevnto, according to the maner and diuerſities of the places, the veſſels ought likewiſe to bee waſhed and made cleane, and looke for old ruſhes that haue beene long gathered, becauſe they are better, &amp; indure longer then the new that are in a manner but halfe growne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the time when the vintage or gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of grapes ſhould be.</head>
               <p>Some gather grapes before the berries bee ripe, and thereby make their wine ſmal, weake,
<pb facs="tcp:3783:14"/>and not durable, others gather them late, and thereby doe not onely hurt their vines, (their ſtrength and vertue being already come forth) but make their wine of leſſe force, &amp; not indure ſo long as otherwiſe it would, ſo that for a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rule to be obſerued, the time to gather grapes is to be knowne, by the ſight and taſt of the ſame, for if the kernell of the grape bee not green, but rather blacke, or of another colour, then the grape wherein it groweth doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly bring forth, it is a ſigne that it is ripe, there are ſome that cruſh the grape betweene their fingers, and if the kernell come forth clean without any meat ſticking vpon it, they ſay the grape is ripe, and that it ſhould be gathered, but if the kernell come forth with the meat vpon it, they ſay it is not ripe: ſome cut a branch out of the ſtocke of a vine, that is thicke, and when a day or two is paſt, they looke if the place where the bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch grew be in like maner as it was whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the branch was taken away, and if the other branches that were about that place be not any thing more growne, they make ready to gather their grapes, but if the place where the branch grew be leſſe then it was, they ſtay gathering their grapes till ſuch time the grapes waxe ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Grapes ought to bee gathered when the Moone is in <hi>Cancer, Leo, Libra, Scorpion, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricornus,</hi> or <hi>Aquarius,</hi> but the Moon going out of thoſe ſignes, they muſt make haſt to gather their grapes. They ſhould bee gathered after three or foure of the clocke, when the dew is all conſumed, and dried vp, &amp; that the aire is hote
<pb facs="tcp:3783:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>and cleare, &amp; the wine will be the ſtronger, and indure the longer: the grapes that ſhine and are not fat, that are not withered, nor rotten in anie part, make the wine ſtronger, and continueth better, and the contrarie worke the contrarie ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Grapes that are ouer ripe make the Wine the ſweeter, but leſſe in ſtrength, and continueth not ſo long as thoſe that are firſt gathered. The grapes that are ouer ſoure, make the Wine ſo much the ſouerer: but thoſe that are indifferent, make the wine ſtrong, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue better. Grapes gathered in the increaſing of the Moone make the wine to continue leſſe time, but thoſe gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the decreaſing, make it better: if the black grapes be boiled in the bottome of the veſſel, the wine will be the redder: if the ripe bee loweſt, it maketh the wine the riper: if the ſoure, it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the wine ſoure, if they be boiled with hony it will be ſweet: if with ſage, it will taſt thereof: and for a generall rule, the wine receiueth the taſt of the thing that is put into it, boiling mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately together for certaine daies. If the grapes that are gathered lie certaine daies in heapes together, the wine will be the riper: if the Muſt boileth in the tun without grapes, it will be good and continue long, but it will bee longer before it waxeth cleare then that which boileth with grapes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How grapes ſhould be gathered and dreſſed to make wine.</head>
               <p>They that put the grapes into the baſkets,
<pb facs="tcp:3783:15"/>doe part and chuſe out the leaues, and if they find any branches or berries that are bitter, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trified or drie, they caſt them away: it is requiſit likewiſe that ſuch as tread the grapes, do take out the leaues, if thoſe that put them in out of the baſkets, do chance to forget themſelues, the leaues bruſed with the wine, make it the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and ſooner to corrupt and become faultie: &amp; of the grapes that are ſoure, putrified and drie, there proceedeth great domage vnto the wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to purge wine, that is made of ſoure grapes.</head>
               <p>It is good to ſeperate all the ſoure grapes, likewiſe ſuch as are corrupt, and keepe them by themſelues from the better ſort, and the Muſt that is made of ſuch grapes, is cured in this manner: ſeeth raine water till it conſumeth half away, and of this ſodden water put thereof into the wine, as much as you eſteem to be the tenth part of the Muſt, and then boile it againe with the wine, till the tenth part conſumeth in the boiling.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To cure the wine that is faulty by reaſon of raine water fallen vpon it.</head>
               <p>If the grapes growing yet vpon the vine, or after they be gathered, be moiſt and wetter then they ſhould be, by reaſon of the water and raine fallen vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, if you perceiue the Muſt be too weake, (which is knowne by taſting therof) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:3783:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>it is put into the veſſell, preſently after the firſt boiling, you may poure it out into other veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeis, becauſe that all the ſlune and thicknes by reaſon of the weight thereof ſinketh to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome: ſome boile it vpon the fire til it conſumeth the twentie part, putting into it the hundreth part of <hi>Geſſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to put Muſt into the veſſels.</head>
               <p>It is good to waſh the veſſels with pure ſalt water, and make them cleane with a ſpunge, &amp; perfume them with inſence before the Muſt be put into them, but fill them not too full, nor yet too little but doe it with a meane, boiling the Muſt till it riſe vp vnto the top, but not run ouer, then with your hands or elſe with glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, (when the muſt is in the veſſels) take away the froth or any other ſkum that riſeth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, &amp; caſt it far off from the fat, for if it it lieth neere, it ingendreth hoarines and cauſeth a filthy ſmell, which two thinges make the wine to turne, wherefore it is conuenient that in ſuch places there be aſweet ſmell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How you muſt keepe Muſt all the yeare.</head>
               <p>Before the grapes are ſtamped, put the Muſt that commeth from them, (the ſame day it is made) in a veſſell by it ſelfe, which ſhall be well clenſed both within and without, fill the veſſell halfe full, and ſtop it well with <hi>Geſſo,</hi> becauſe the Muſt may continue ſweet a long time, but if
<pb facs="tcp:3783:16"/>you put the veſſell (being ſtopped with copper) into a wel, it wil continue much longer, becauſe that not being able to boile, it will alwaies bee Muſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to know if there be water in the wine or Muſt, and how to ſeperate the one from the other.</head>
               <p>Put into the Muſt either peares, or mulbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and if there be water in the wine or muſt, they will ſinke vnto the bottome, and if there be none, they will ſwim on the top: others put the wine into a new earthen pot, not waſhed, &amp; let it continue therein for the ſpace of two daies that the water may diſtil out of the pot, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing remaine but the wine: others annointing a ſpunge with oile, ſtop the mouth of the veſſell therewith, and then turne it cleane ouer, and if there be water in the wine, it will ſoake into the ſpunge. Water is taken from wine in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, put alum into the wine veſſell, then ſtop the mouth of the veſſell with a ſpunge dipped in oile, then turn it in ſuch ſort, that there may no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but water iſſue forth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>When you ſhall draw or rack wine, and open the veſſels.</head>
               <p>You muſt racke wine when the wind is in the North, but neuer when it is in the South, the weakeſt in the ſpring time, the ſtrongeſt in the ſummer, but thoſe wines that grow in drie
<pb facs="tcp:3783:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>places, ſhall bee racked after the ſunne is in the equinoxiall hiuernall. When wine is racked the Moone being in the full, it maketh it ſharp: when wine is taken from his lees it maketh it more ſubtill and weake: it is neceſſarie to racke wine when the Moone increaſeth, and is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the earth, and to obſerue the riſing of the ſtars, becauſe the lees (when the ſtars riſe) doth moue &amp; ſtir vp, eſpecially when roſes bud forth, and vines begin to ſpring, when the veſſell is opeued, it is good to ſpend the wine that is on the top of the veſſell, and that which is in the bottome, and to keep that which is in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle thereof, becauſe it is of more ſtrength, and continueth longeſt, for the wine that is neer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the mouth of the veſſell, as being neereſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the aire, is weaker, becauſe it caſteth foorth a vapor from it, &amp; that which is in the bottome, or in the lees, doth ſoone decay. It is requiſite when the wine is drawne into other veſſels, not to let it run at the mouth of the veſſels, but ſomewhat lower, that it ſtop not at the mouth, but haue ſome aire in the running out, leaſt you feare it will become ſoure, which if you doubt, let it not take any aire, but make the vent of greene willowes, the barke or outward peele ſcraped cleane away: if you open the fat by day, you muſt beware that the heat of the ſun touch not the wine, and if you open it by night, you muſt keepe the light of the Moone from it, and when the fats are emptie, you muſt waſh them preſently with ſalt water, and aſhes, or drie them with clay yearth, if the wine be weake,
<pb facs="tcp:3783:17"/>but if it be very ſtrong, it is ſufficient to cloſe it vp on all ſides, becauſe the ſmell and ſtrength of the wine preſerueth the veſſels.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What time and how you ſhall taſt wine.</head>
               <p>Some taſt wines when the wind bloweth in the North, but it is better to taſt when it bloweth in the Eaſt, becauſe the Eaſtwind mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the wine more, and ſheweth what it is. It is not good to taſt wine being faſting, becauſe it ſpoileth the taſt, neither is it good to taſt it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter much meat or drink. Further, he that taſteth Wine, muſt not haue eaten any bitter or ſalt meat, nor haue eaten much, but a little meat, &amp; that it be diſgeſted. Some ſeeking to deceiue thoſe that buy wine, take a new veſſell, which they dip into old wine that is good, and hath a good ſmell, and then put that wine into it that they meane to ſell, which I ſet downe to giue you inſtructions that you be not deceiued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to know wines that will indure and continue long.</head>
               <p>Herein you muſt haue care oftentimes to ſmell vnto your wines, leaſt there bee any alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the lees, ingendring hoarines or white mouldines that groweth vnder the buts, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners other like things, becauſe that ſuch things are ſignes that the wine decaieth, but if no ſuch things appear, it is to be iudged that the wine will continue long. Some borie a little Wine,
<pb facs="tcp:3783:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>and being cold, they taſt it, and as they find that in the taſt, ſo they eſteeme the reſt of the wine will fall out in goodnes, but it is requiſite to taſt the wine in the middle of the but.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of diuers infections that happen vnto wine.</head>
               <p>It happeneth vnto wine by meanes of the corrupt wateriſhnes that is in the vines, or in the veſſels, that it infecteth and ſpoileth by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers meanes, wrought in it by the ſtrange heat thereof, as you ſhall perceiue, for if there fal into it a little lees, or a little wine that hath lees in it, and bee put into the veſſell without opening it, it will conuert into hoarines, and infect the wine: beſides this, all other wine that is put into it, is thereby infected. And if any of that wine be put into a good butt, or be mingled with other Wine, it doth infect it, and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it into the ſame corrupt nature: further, wine that is perfect good &amp; ſtrong, &amp; eſpeciallie that which is ſweet aboue meaſure. When the weather is hote, the veſſel not being ful, and not cloſe aboue, the heat and moiſtnes thereof iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth, the coldnes and drineſſe therof remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, whereby it turneth to be ſoure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>At what time wine doth ſoone change, and corrupt.</head>
               <p>All wines doe oftentimes change in the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Charles waine, and in the Solſtitio eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and in the dog daies, which commonly are called Cumma, and generally when the wind is Weſtwardly, and in heat, or froſt, or in great
<pb facs="tcp:3783:18"/>tempeſts, or by ouermuch wind, or by earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, or thunders, or at the ſpringing of ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and of vines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to preuent the changing of wine.</head>
               <p>Salt burned, and put into wine, doth keep it from changing, and that it boileth not vp more then it ſhould, nor that it riſeth with any great ſcum: put ſweet almonds into black grapes, and letting them ſtand, they conſerue the Wine. Grapes being gathered, the kernels take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forth and mixed with ſand, and put into the Muſt, or wine being ſodden, maketh it fat, and indure long. Geſſo when it is firſt put into the Wine maketh it bitter, but in time, the bitterneſſe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away, and the <hi>Geſſo</hi> worketh this effect, that the wine indureth a long time, &amp; ſuffereth it not to change: the quantitie that muſt bee put in, if the wine bee ſmall and of a humide taſt, or troubled with tempeſts, is the hundreth part of <hi>Geſſo.</hi> But if it bee ſtrong by reaſon of the ſtrength, the halfe of an hundreth part of geſſo will ſerue. Wines that change being taken from their infected lees, and put vnto the lees of good wine, they will indure long. Some men put into Wine the fruit of the Ledar tree, well bruſed to pouder, and therewith doe mingle gaules likewiſe bruſed to pouder. Some bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the aſhes of a vine being burnt, with fennel ſeed, mixing them together, doe put them into wine. Others put the wine that changeth into other veſſels, &amp; remoue it into another houſe, for if it be hurt by reaſon of heat, they remoue it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a freſher place, and if it ſpoile by reaſon of the
<pb facs="tcp:3783:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>humiditie and coldnes of the place, where it is, they put it in ſome other place that is drier and hote Clay put into wine after it hath boiled, doth purge it, drawing downe with it the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection thereof into the lees, but if it be ſtamped it maketh the wine of good ſauor, and ſweet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the birds that eat of it in winter time, are preſerued thereby and liue, for it comforteth the wine and maketh it continue long. A little yuie both white and black put into wine, maketh it continue, the like doth ſodden wine, mixing a third part thereof in the muſt. Wheat flower maketh it durable. The root of the pine tree, keepeth wine from changing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent infection to preſerue wine, which is called Panaccia.</head>
               <p>Take two ounces of Aloes, two ounces of inſence, &amp; two ounces of <hi>amomo,</hi> bind all theſe faſt in a linnen cloath, &amp; put them into the veſſel after the wine is therein, and that it hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and of this mixture, put into each veſſell a meaſure called a <hi>cluchiero,</hi> full, then ſhake it out of the cloath, &amp; leaue the pouder in the wine, and three daies after do it again with roots of canes</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To keepe wine from changing.</head>
               <p>Let it boile two or three daies in the grapes, &amp; draw it out in the month of Februarie, and of this boile the third part &amp; mix them together, then into twelue corſes of wine put a common poringer ful of ſalt. Or doe it in this ſort, and it will be excellent and pleaſant to drinke what wine ſoeuer it bee: ſcum the grapes, and all the Wine that is not boiled with the
<pb facs="tcp:3783:19"/>grapes boile it on the fire, and ſcum it, and ſo put it in the veſſell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to remedie wine that is changed.</head>
               <p>Temper wine that is turned or changed, with a good quantitie of hony, throwing it into the veſſell wherein the wine is. Then ſtir it in the butt with a ſticke, at the bung, letting it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſo, and the wine will cleare it ſelfe, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the honny maketh the dregs that are in the wine to deſcend into the bottome: it is good to put into the veſſell where the wine is changed, (at the time when grapes are gathering) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers berries of grapes, which ſhall lie therein in ſteed of the mother, becauſe thoſe grapes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a certaine time, will turne the wine that is changed, to his right goodnes and ſauor. And before you doe any thing vnto wine that is changed, you muſt draw it foorth and take it from the infected lees. Alſo put the wine into veſſels out of the which wine hath ben newly taken forth, that it may clarefie therein, and let it remaine therein as long as it is needfull, but if there be any quantitie of wine, it muſt not bee done all at one time, but a little at once, that the wine doe not extinguiſh the heat of the grapes and hinder not the boiling thereof, wherein it clarefieth, and how little a time the Muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth in the grapes, ſo much the ſtronger it worketh. Wine is clarefied &amp; made good when you beat twentie graines of pepper and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>peſtachie,</hi> putting thereto a little wine, then
<pb facs="tcp:3783:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>put afterward thereto ſixe ceſternes of Wine, hauing firſt ſtirred euery thing together, then letting them reſt quietly, that they may worke, a foggie wine is preſently cleare, if in a ſexter of wine you put ſeuen kernels of a pine aple, ſtirring them often, and then letting them ſtand, by little and little the Wine will cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refie, that you may draw it and vſe it. Some clarefie it with white of egs, and with ſalt, but take white ſtones out of a riuer and bake them in an ouen till they begin to cracke, then beat them into pouder, take likewiſe white ſalt bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten into ſmall pouder, and in a veſſell of ten meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers put ſix ounces of pouder of ſtones, &amp; foure of ſalt, and ſtirring them together, put the wine into the veſſell, and if for euery meaſure you put therein two or three egs it will be good. This may be done likewiſe with the ſame ſtones not baked, being beaten to ſmall pouder, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſalt, and it ſhall bee good to put therevnto a little hony, becauſe hony that is red, reſtoreth the colour of white wine that hath loſt the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and hony is clammy, and heauy, and a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruer of all liquors. But if the wine bee ouer much troubled and thicke, put thereto a little more of each of the thinges aforeſaid, becauſe thoſe things, by reaſon of the waight, do keepe downe the lees, and driue the thickeneſſe to the bottome that it can not ſo eaſily riſe vp vnto the top and it giueth likewiſe no euill ſauour to the wine. But if the wine be ſo much troubled, that being as it were rank and in a maner fatty like oile, the naturall heat thereof being in a maner
<pb facs="tcp:3783:20"/>wholy extinguiſhed, then there is no remedie to be had, no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a dead man. It will cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refy alſo in this maner, if you put into a veſſel of forty meaſures, twentie egs, which you muſt beat wel in a baſen or boule with a clean ſpoon, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put into them a poringer ful of Tartarum, &amp; mingle them together, adding thereto a little wine, then put it into the veſſell, which done, ſtir them well at the bung with a clouen woodden ſtick, &amp; thruſt it oftentimes downe into the lees, then put it againe into the veſſel, and when it is clear take out al the thick matter on the ſides of the veſſell: but you muſt vnderſtand, that into white wine you muſt only put white of egs, but into claret or red both whites &amp; yolks, and into Wine that is much troubled, you muſt put in more quantitie: further in place of Tartarum, you may put ſalt, and laſtly there is put into the veſſel a little clear water. Wine is clarefied, and holpen of the il ſauor &amp; changing, if in a veſſel of three meaſures, you put halfe a pound of cleare roch alum, &amp; as much ſucket of roſes, with eight pounds of hony. In this maner, ſeeth the honny very wel, &amp; ſkum it, &amp; when it is cold, put the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum into it, being beaten into ſmall pouder, and the ſucket diſſolued, which mingle all in a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of wine, then put them into the veſſell, &amp; ſtir them wel with a clouen ſtick, &amp; the veſſell being open, let it ſtand ſo till the next day, &amp; the ſecond or third day it will be cleare: but if the wine bee much troubled &amp; ſpoiled, put ſo much the more of the thinges aforeſaid: neuertheles you muſt vnderſtand that before you do it, you muſt draw
<pb facs="tcp:3783:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Wine out into another veſſell, and take it from the infected lees.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How wine and the veſſels are preſerued from hoarines.</head>
               <p>If wine be hoary or haue any other euil ſauor, take a white grapes ſprigs with the roots, and ſet it in the ground vnder the butt, in ſuch ſort that the roots may be right againſt the mouth vpon the butt, &amp; put the branches in the wine a handfull deepe, at the bung aboue the butt, let it ſtand there three daies, and till it looſeth the euill ſauor. Some take a white grape branch &amp; put the head of it into the veſſell in place of the bung, and ſet it on the ground, ſetting it faſt that it ſtirreth not, and ſo the hoarines daily iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth forth by the branch, by which meanes the euil ſauor deminiſheth. For the ſame, take Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers that are bitter, being hanged on three or more pack thrids, put them in at the bung that they may deſcend into the wine, letting them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine therein fifteene daies or a month, &amp; they remedie the wine &amp; the veſſel of the hoarines. It is ſaid likewiſe it is done, if euery morning and euening there bee hanged in the wine a bundle of ſage, that toucheth not the wine, and being taken out againe, waſh it in water, ſtopping the bung well. Take likewiſe a handfull of the hearbe called <hi>Nierella</hi> or <hi>Morella,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bound with a little ſtring, in the morning put it into the veſſell at the bung, that it deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend not into the wine aboue two fingers deep, and the cord being made faſt vpon the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, ſtop the veſſell hard, and let it hang
<pb facs="tcp:3783:21"/>therein the ſpace of one day, and at night take it out, putting other freſh hearbs therein, letting them remaine therein till the next day in the morning, which you muſt do for three or foure daies one after the other. Thoſe veſſels that are hoarie are cured in this maner, put a quantitie of ſleacked lime, into a butt of twelue baſkets, and put into the ſame butt being ſtopped, either boiled water or wine, &amp; let it bee ſo well ſtopped that no aire iſſue forth. Let it ſtand a little ſpace, then roule it vp and downe diuers times: that done, open it, and let the liquor that is in it iſſue forth, &amp; waſh the butt againe with cold water. Or otherwiſe, put gineper (being ſodden in a chaldron of wine, and that is ſeething hote) into the veſſels, &amp; do as I ſaid before, and it will bee better, if both the remedies be vſed one after the other, that is, the ſecond after the firſt. In the ſame maner the fats are remedied, but becauſe they cannot bee ſtopped in ſuch ſort as the buts may be, they are couered with clothes, ſo that they cannot ſend foorth any aire: the buts are preſerued from mouldineſſe, if when they are to be emptied, they ſtand open vntill there bee but a ſmal quantitie of wine in them, and that they bee very well dried, and after that well waſhed with ſalt water, or wine, or elſe not emptieng foorth that little quantitie of Wine that is in them, the butt being wel ſtopped, that the ſmell or ſent may not iſſue forth.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:3783:21"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
